Ready, we are דף ג Daf Gimmel in חולין Chullin and pick
up on the bottom of דף ב עמוד ב. Daf Bet Amud
Bet.
Now I want to say something, you know, the first discussion here
might have felt a little bit a little frustrated in that it
created a very what I consider artificial question about the משנה Mishnah
is it talking about לכתחילה lechatchila or בדיעבד? bedieved? It forces itself
to say it's talking about לכתחילה בדיעבד. lechatchila b'diavad, But anyway, and
then it gave an answer. This is a classic move in the
beginning of a מסכת masechet that often it will focus on what's
a very side issue, sometimes very often a linguistic issue about the
משנה Mishnah
and sometimes something that one would feel is not such a big
question and does not deserve demand too much time but becomes the
focus of the first discussion. But often this is used as a
way of introducing some major themes that are going to be coming
up in the מסכת masechet and you find this in a number
of מסכתות masechtos this way.
The beginning of בבא קמא Bava Kamma it says ארבע אבות arba
avos is the תולדה tolada like it or not like it and
it uses it to
even overview of all of the categories of נזיקין. nezikin. And this
happens in a number of מסכתות, masechtos, sometimes there's a sense that
it's a particularly very late סוגיא sugya that was constructed for this
purpose. So anyway, that's what you have right here. We created a
question to force ourselves, we sort of insisted that the משנה Mishnah
is first indicated לכתחילה lechatchila and then indicated בדיעבד, bedieved. and we're
going to now continue with that but use this as a way
to see four or five different answers today that all lay out
for us different degrees of לכתחילה lechatchila and בדיעבד bedieved, when it
comes to שחיטה. shechita. So in a way it introduces us to,
you know, major questions about שחיטה: shechita: who can שחט, shecht, under
what circumstances can you שחט, shecht, what's לכתחילה, lechatchila what's בדיעבד, bedieved
certain debates about that, and that's going to be the remainder of
today's דף. daf. Okay, so we're going to pick up now at
the bottom of דף ב עמוד ב, Daf Bet Amud Bet, two
lines on the bottom: האי טמא דאיתמא במאי. Hai tamei de-itma be-mai.
So we're wrapping up the first explanation that said that the questions
of לכתחילה lechatchila, and בדיעבד bedieved, were if a person is טמא
tamei then totally לכתחילה lechatchila they can שחט shecht חולין, chullin, even
חולין chullin that was treated like הקדש hekdesh with purity, but they
can't treat הקדש. hekdesh. And if they did and if they שחט
shechted הקדש, hekdesh, then it's okay if they know that they didn't
touch it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara is just wrapping this
up. האי טמא דאיתמא במאי? Hai tamei de-itma be-mai? This טמא tamei
person, how did he become טמא tamei that's doing the
שחיטה? shechita? אילימא דאיתמא במת, Ileima de-itma be-meis, if he became טמא
tamei with a dead body, and now we quote from this week's
פרשה: parsha: בחלל חרב אמר רחמנא. Be-chalal cherev amar rachmana. The תורה
Torah says by a corpse of a sword, top of דף ג
עמוד א, Daf Gimmel Amud Aleph, which is a הלכה halachic principle
of חרב הרי הוא כחלל, cherev harei hu ke-chalal, that a sword
is just like the corpse itself. What does this mean? It means
that there's an interesting הלכה halacha in הלכות טומאת מת. Hilchos Tumas
Meis. The corpse itself is considered אבי אבות הטומאה, avi avos hatuma,
a granddaddy of טומאות. tumas. Okay, the person who touches it is
called an אב הטומאה. av hatuma. אב Av is normally the source
of טומאה. tuma. Because טומאת מת tumas meis is more powerful and
it continues and it has one more stage in it, the actual
corpse is considered the אבי אבות. avi avos. Now normally when טומאה
tuma transfers from one thing to another, it goes down a level.
So the אבי אבות, avi avos, the grandfather, becomes the אב הטומאה,
av hatuma, the person who touches it. When he touches something it
becomes a ראשון, rishon, first degree derivative, then a שני sheni and
so on. Because of this פסוק pasuk by מת meis where it
says בחלל חרב, be-chalal cherev, the corpse of a sword, we make
a דרשה, drasha, the sword that killed the corpse, right, if you
imagine in a battlefield a guy has been slaughtered by a sword,
that sword is just like the corpse itself. So that if a
metal object touches a מת, meis, touches a dead body, it doesn't
go down a level, it retains the same level of טומאה. tuma.
It is an אבי אבות. avi avos. And we apply that one
step down as well and we say that if an אב הטומאה,
av hatuma, if I touched a dead body and then I touched
a metal object, a metal vessel, that it does not go down
a level and it remains an אב הטומאה. av hatuma. Okay, so
this is a special law in הלכות טומאת מת Hilchos Tumas Meis
that metal objects do not at least retain when it touches the
מת meis or the person who touched the מת meis retain the
same level of טומאה. tuma. How is this relevant for us? Well
we're assuming that the knife is a metal knife, makes sense. Now
if I touched the מת, meis, okay, because I'm טמא tamei and
that's what the issue here, then I'm an אב הטומאה. av hatuma.
I now touch my metal knife to שחט, shecht, okay, it doesn't
go down a level. That's this principle of חרב כחלל. cherev ke-chalal.
It's an אב הטומאה. av hatuma. Okay, now if I שחט, shecht,
even if I don't touch the meat, this knife which is an
אב הטומאה av hatuma is touching the meat and it should make
the meat טמא. tamei. So how can we say that that is
allowed? Okay, now you might want to say, well maybe I didn't
touch the knife, maybe it's a wooden handle, whatever. So תוספות Tosafos
and רש"י Rashi both point out that you know this whole introduction
of this category about metal and its particular power here is not
even really needed. Even if this wasn't a metal knife, it would
be the same problem. Why? Because the מת meis is an אבי
אבות, avi avos, I'm an אב, av, I touch the knife, I
make it into
a ראשון... rishon... The point is even if I'm not touching the
meat, the knife is touching the meat and it should make it
טמא. tamei. So how does it solve the problem that I don't
touch the meat? So the גמרא Gemara says לתמיא לסכין, letamyei lesakin,
so let me be מטמא metamei the
סכין sakin and the סכין sakin will go ותמטיה לבשר vetimtei lebasar
and we'll be מטמא metamei the בשר. basar. So how does it
help that I'm not touching the meat? אלא Ella says the גמרא
Gemara דאיטמי בשרץ. de'itmei besheretz.
All right, I didn't become טמא tamei by touching a dead body,
I became טמא tamei by touching a dead rodent. Okay, or I
don't know, a carcass of a dead animal. So in that type
of a case, the animal is an אב, Av, right, because only
the מת meis is the אבי אבות, Avi Avot, the grandaddy. The
מת meis starts one level higher. A normal thing is an אב,
Av, a source. I touch it, I become a ראשון. Rishon. I
touch my knife, metal or not, there's no special דין din of
metal when it's not מת. meis. So the knife becomes a שני.
Sheini. Okay, right, אב, Av, I become a ראשון, Rishon, the knife
becomes... actually forget that. If I am
a ראשון, Rishon, I can only be מטמא metamei food, I cannot
be מטמא metamei כלי, klee, vessels. That's more to the point. So
in that case, I can't be מטמא metamei the knife if I'm
a ראשון Rishon and therefore everything is okay. So that's answer number
one.
Answer number two, ואיבעית אימא, ve'iba'it eima, לעולם דאיטמי במת. le'olam de'itmei
bemeis. This is a more interesting answer. I did become טמא tamei
with a מת. meis. So how come then it didn't transfer to
the knife and the knife to the meat since I'm now an
אב? Av? וכגון שבדק קרומית של קנה ושחט בה. ukegon shebadak kerumit
shel kaneh veshachat bah. This person checked
a
reed and he sharpened a reed or he checked it here meaning
to make sure that it was sharp enough and he used a
reed, like a hard reed, like a bamboo reed is a way
to think about it, to שחט. shecht. דתניא, detanya, as we taught
in a ברייתא, Braisa, בכל שוחטין, bechol shochtin, you can שחט shecht
with everything, בין בצור בין בזכוכית, bein betzur bein bizchuchit, whether you
want to use a rock or a piece of glass, בין בקרומית
של קנה, bein bikrumit shel kaneh, or a reed, as long as
it's sharp enough and it's smooth, it has no nicks and it
does the job. Okay, so incidentally in that, as I was saying
when we started, you know, it's using this question of how to
read the משנה Mishna as a way of introducing a lot of
ideas relating to שחיטה, shechitah, almost as a table of contents, as
an introduction to concepts in the מסכתא. masechta. So besides this issue
about טומאה tumah which is really secondary, here we use it to
introduce a point about that you know what object you can use
to שחט. shecht. You don't need a knife, which is surprising. Anything
that's sharp enough and smooth enough is fine even if it's not
a knife. Now תוספות Tosfos here has an interesting question. What? Well,
I'm going to tell you. תוספות Tosfos here has an interesting discussion
which if you might remember came up when we did זבחים Zvachim
and מנחות, Menachos, that they said that you needed a כלי klee
for שחיטה. shechitah. We actually learned it out from a very troubling
פסוק pasuk from אברהם Avraham and יצחק, Yitzchak, ויקח את המאכלת לשחוט
את בנו. vayikach es hama'achelet lishchot es beno. From there you see
you need a כלי klee to do שחיטה. shechitah. So anyway, תוספות
Tosfos asks two questions. One question תוספות Tosfos says is these things
here are not a כלי klee for the purpose of טומאה. tumah.
In the classic category where we determine what's considered a vessel or
not, is it a vessel for טומאה tumah laws? These types of
things, a sharp rock, a sharp piece of glass, those are not
vessels for טומאה. tumah. So תוספות Tosfos says all right, even if
we say you need a vessel for שחיטה, shechitah, we don't literally
mean a vessel that would be counted as a vessel in other
places. We just mean something that is like
fashioned to serve that purpose. But then the definition, the requirement becomes
almost
purposeless because basically you're saying it has to do the job, so
what does it even mean to call it a כלי? klee? So
that's one interesting point, that for all intents and purposes you don't
need something that's a formally recognized vessel. You don't need a שחיטה
shechitah knife, like there's no qualifications of what constitutes the knife, you
might imagine that right, oh there's a שחיטה shechitah knife and it
has to look like this, has to look like that, no, there's
no definition of what the knife has to be. It just has
to be sharp enough and smooth enough to do it. Now the
מאכלת Ma'achelet issue is about a כלי klee for
קדשים. kodshim. But even there תוספות Tosfos has a question whether you
need it to be a כלי שרת klee shareit or not. And
that was a question that we had mentioned there because תוספות Tosfos
says some of the things that looks like you can שחט shecht
with are things that normally are not allowed to be a כלי
שרת. klee shareit. Like תוספות Tosfos has a hard time imagining, for
example, now this is talking about normal שחיטה shechitah not קדשים, kodshim,
but some of these things are significant enough to constitute a כלי
שרת. klee shareit. So that becomes an interesting question on two fronts,
as I said, number one is for normal שחיטה, shechitah, what we
see here is there's no formal requirement of what the knife has
to be and it doesn't really need to be a כלי klee
in other recognized as a כלי klee in other circumstances
and even for שחיטת קדשים shechitat kodshim the interesting question is whether
it has to be a כלי שרת klee shareit or not and
that תוספות Tosfos here seriously questions. It's also not clear in the
רמב"ם Rambam whether it has to be a כלי שרת, klee shareit,
so that's an interesting question as well and we remember for שחיטת
קדשים shechitat kodshim it doesn't require a כהן. kohen. So if it
doesn't require a כהן, kohen, it's logical to assume you wouldn't need
a כלי שרת klee shareit either although there are other גמרות Gemoras
that talk about the שחיטה shechitah knife being מקדיש makdish the animal,
sanctifying the animal, so it's a very it's an issue that is
not so clear, that there seem to be different indications.
the you see ציפורה Tzipporah taking a flint and using doing circumcision.
That's מילה! milah!
Right, which is meaning different.
All right, well, there are differences. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
goes on. Okay, so that's one issue about what you're using as
your שחיטה shechita knife. אביי אמר, Abaye amar, now אביי Abaye goes
back to answer this question of the לכתחילה בדיעבד, lechatchila bedieved. but
he's going to take a different tack, not about טומאה, tumah, and
get closer to the heart of questions about what constitutes good שחיטה
shechita לכתחילה lechatchila and what constitutes it בדיעבד. bedieved And he's going
to focus on the person who's doing it. So let's take a
look. אביי אמר הכי קתני, Abaye amar hachi katani, here's how you
read the משנה. Mishnah.
הכל שוחטין, Hakol shochtin, everybody can do שחיטה, shechita, ואפילו כותי, v'afilu
Kuti, even a Samaritan. Now sometimes כותי Kuti is a euphemistic way
of saying a non-Jew, but here it literally does mean a Samaritan.
And here's the issue with Samaritans. Number one is are they Jewish
or not Jewish? Right? The Torah says in the end in the
book of ירמיה Yirmiyah after the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash was destroyed
that נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar put the Samaritans into Israel and that they they
worshiped their god and they worshiped our God. So there's a whole
question about whether they converted or not and are they Jewish or
not. That's question number one. Question number two is even if they're
Jewish, because as we're going to find out later a non-Jew, even
if he does it correctly, is categorically excluded from שחיטה shechita and
is invalid, so it doesn't matter if it's technically correct. But let's
assume a Samaritan is Jewish. Okay, so now he's not categorically excluded.
Is he going to do it correctly? Well, it was clearly known
that Samaritans kept a lot of Jewish laws, right? That was through
Second Temple period and so on. But there were some areas in
which they kept differently than the than the Jews. So the question
is is are they following the same system of laws for שחיטה
shechita as we are? Even if they are following the same system
of laws for שחיטה shechita as we are, the big question that
that plays out in the גמרא Gemara is do they care about
making other people sin? Particularly if those other people are the, are
the, you know, are the non-Samaritan Jews who there was obviously a
lot of antagonism between. Okay, so the assumption might be for themselves
they'll do a good שחיטה shechita and they'll follow the same laws
we would. But if they're שחטינג shechting it for us, they might
not care about making us sin and they might not believe that
there's a prohibition of לפני עור לא תתן מכשול, lifnei iver lo
titein michshol, and particularly in a case where there's this antagonism. So
maybe if they're doing it for us we can't trust that they
did it correctly. Those are like the collection of issues around the
Samaritan. So let's take a look at how אביי Abaye parses this
out about whether a Samaritan can do the שחיטה. shechita. Yeah.
Didn't we say that כל מצוה שהחזיקו בה כותים, kol mitzvah shehicheziku
ba Kutim, yes,
but the question is yes, anyone that they are מקפיד makpid on
for themselves? But as opposed to
לפני עור?
lifnei iver? Right. Insofar as it's a מצוה mitzvah of שחיטה? shechita?
Yes. But they don't hold the מצוה mitzvah of לפני עור. lifnei
iver. So if they're it says they're being very מקפיד makpid on
their for themselves eating kosher meat.
Okay so let's take a look. You don't get it? They don't
care about other people sinning. No but if they're if they're
already doing the שחטינג, shechting, they're going to do it right because...
No, not if they know that they're doing the שחטינג shechting for
you and they think that anyway you're constantly oppressing them and giving
them a hard time and they don't like you and there's a
lot of antagonism and they don't think they're doing any עבירה aveira
by feeding you טרף treif meat. Okay, they're מקפיד makpid for themselves
for שחיטה. shechita. All right, let's take a look. So הכי קתני,
hachi katani,
this is what it says. הכל שוחטין, Hakol shochtin, everybody can do
שחיטה, shechita, ואפילו כותי, v'afilu Kuti, even a Samaritan. במה דברים אמורים,
B'meh devarim amurim, when is this true? כשישראל עומד על גביו, kshe'Yisrael
omeid al gabav, when it's under direct supervision of ישראל. Yisrael. So
you're sure that they're doing it technically correctly. So then the only
question is is whether they're considered Jewish or not. So yes they're
considered Jewish, but it's direct observation of the Jew so it's okay.
That's when it's okay לכתחילה. lechatchila אבל יוצא ונכנס לא ישחוט. Aval
yotzei v'nichnas lo yishchot. Now here we get into general questions about
what does supervision mean, right? We're getting supervision of of restaurants and
so on. Do you need to directly be there all the time?
You know some supervisions will have a משגיח תמידי, mashgiach temidi, right?
Others are יוצא ונכנס. yotzei v'nichnas. So are you there all the
time or are you popping in at random times to check up?
Okay? So here אביי Abaye is saying that we normally if we
suspect somebody is not going to do a good job by שחיטה
shechita you have to have constant supervision, עומד על גביו. omeid al
gabav. If you're just יוצא ונכנס yotzei v'nichnas popping in and out,
that's not good. Okay, that's the... So ואם שחט, v'im shachat, now
what's the case in the משנה Mishnah we're talking about בדיעבד b'diavad.
it's okay? He went ahead and he שחט-ed shachat and there was
no משגיח תמידי, mashgiach temidi, it was only popping in and out.
There's still a way to salvage the situation. What is it? חותך
כזית בשר, choteich kezayis basar, take a piece of the meat that
he just שחט-ed, shachat ונותן לו, v'nosein lo, and say, 'Here, you
try it first!' It's like, it's like, you know, the king's taster,
right, when they're afraid of being poisoned. First you give it to,
you know, the cook to taste. Okay, you taste it first! ונותן
לו, v'nosein lo, אכל לו, achal lo, if he eats it, then
מותר לאכול משחיטתו, mutar leechol mishchitasa, so you can eat the rest.
לא אכל לו, lo achal lo, if he refused to eat it,
'I'm a vegetarian,' whatever he says, אסור לאכול משחיטתו, assur leechol mishchitasa,
so you cannot. And here's exactly the idea. Number one we assume
he's a Jew, number two we assume that they know how to,
they do the same שחיטה shechita laws as we do and they
do it carefully, but the only concern is is that he doesn't
care that he's going to make us sin. And maybe as I
said with given the reality of the antagonism, maybe he בדווקא bedafka
wants to make us sin. But anyway, that's the concern. So the
way to solve it is either you have constant supervision or if
he himself will eat from it. then you know that he did
it correctly because he wouldn't eat טרייף treif food and then you
can go ahead and eat from it as well. So that's the
לכתחילה בדיעבד. L'chatchila b'diavad. לכתחילה lechatchila. you do it with direct supervision,
בדיעבד b'diavad he can do it even without direct supervision if he
ate from it. Okay, so this is אביי Abaye using this as
an opportunity to introduce into the conversation who are the people that
can do the שחיטה shechita and under what circumstances, what degree of
supervision do we need? Sally, did you want to say something? Because
I... Oh, it doesn't have to be a כזית. kezayit. You know,
I didn't even pay attention to that, but maybe it is, maybe
he doesn't hold of the problem of חצי שיעור. chatzi shiur. So,
I don't know, that is a good point,
I didn't think about the fact that כזית kezayit might be דוקא.
davka. Right. Okay. Now, then we just end the
משנה. mishna. חוץ מחרש שוטה וקטן. chutz mecheresh shoteh vekatan. This, although
which is good for the כותי, kuti, is not good for חרש
שוטה וקטן. cheresh shoteh vekatan. ואפילו בדיעבד נמי לא. veafilu bedieved nami
lo. If it's direct supervision, that's okay, that's the end of the
משנה. mishna. But if it's not direct supervision, there's no way of
salvaging the situation, because for them, we're concerned whether they technically did
it correctly, not whether you know, not whether they were willfully trying
to trip somebody up. So for them even if they were to
eat the meat, like, whatever, they think they did it correctly, they're
just not careful enough, so it's not going to work, there's no
way to salvage it after the fact. Why? שמא ישהו שמא ידרסו
ושמא יחלידו, shema yishu shema yidresu veshema yachlidu, because they might have
put pressure or they might have paused, they might have done things
that invalidated it. So as opposed to the כותי kuti where he
knows what he's doing and the only question then is will he
be willing to eat from it himself, in this type of a
case, they might have accidentally messed it up without knowing, so there's
no way to salvage it without direct supervision, there was no direct
supervision. And then the last line of the משנה, mishna, וכולן ששחטו,
vechulan sheshachatu, and if anybody שחט shachat and it was observed it's
okay. אהי? Ahai? Which case is that going on? אילמא חרש שוטה
וקטן? Ilema cheresh shoteh vekatan? If it's on this case exactly about
the חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh vekatan, אלא קאי? ala kai? So
we were just talking about that. Why do you have to say
וכולן, vechulan, everybody? ואם שחטו מיבעי ליה? veim shachatu mibaei lei? Should
it have said if they, the חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh vekatan,
slaughtered it with direct supervision it's okay. אלא אכותי? Ela akuti? So
it's going on the case of the כותי. kuti. הא אמרת
כשישראל עומד על גביו שחט אפילו לכתחילה? Ha amart kesheyisrael omed al
gabav shachat afilu lechatchila? But that was how you interpreted the beginning
of the משנה, mishna, that with direct supervision it's okay even לכתחילה.
lechatchila So why would it be saying it again at the end
and make it sound that it's only בדיעבד? bedieved הגמרא Hagemara says
קשיא. kashya. Alright, that's a difficulty. The word וכולן vechulan would not
refer here to more than the חרש שוטה וקטן. cheresh shoteh vekatan.
Okay, so
here's אביי's Abaye read, introduces the idea number one about certain principles
about כותים kutim and number two about when somebody might not be
doing a good job because you're afraid that not that they don't
know what to do, but they're not, they're trying to mess up
or they're not being careful, but they do know, so that how
to solve it either through direct supervision or through seeing if they'll
eat from the meat itself. Okay, because of this, רבא Rava now
uses this as an opportunity to question whether you actually need direct
supervision. And here becomes as I said a fascinating question about like
we see it today in restaurants. Do you need משגיח תמידי mashgiach
tamidi or do you need יוצא ונכנס? yotze venichnas? Okay, what is
the general standard do you need to make sure that people are
doing what they have to be doing? So let's take a look
at what רבא Rava says. Okay, so אמר רבא, amar Rava, so
says
רבא, Rava, ויוצא ונכנס לכתחילה לא? veyotze venichnas lechatchila lo? Are you
telling me that somebody just popping in and out, that's not good?
That you have, you need a, you need direct
supervision? והתנן, Vehatnan, we taught by
יין נסך, yayin nesech, המניח עובד כוכבים בחנותו, hamaniach oved kochavim bachanuto,
וישראל יוצא ונכנס. veyisrael yotze venichnas. You left a non-Jew in your
store and you have all these barrels of wine and the and
you're concerned that the non-Jew might touch the wine. And if he
touches the wine he makes it into סתם יינם stam yeinam and
it's no longer kosher. So what type of supervision do you need
to make sure that he's not touching the wine? So the משנה
mishna says you leave him in your store וישראל יוצא ונכנס veyisrael
yotze venichnas and you're popping in and out from the store, מותר,
mutar, it's okay. The fact that you're popping in and out is
enough to keep him honest and make sure that he's not going
to touch the wine. So you see יוצא ונכנס yotze venichnas suffices.
So the גמרא gemara says
התם, hatam, so the answer, גמרא gemara answers back, מי קתני מניח?
mi katani maniach? You're allowed to do it לכתחילה? lechatchila. המניח קתני.
hamaniach katani. If you left him in your store and you popped
in and out, it's okay בדיעבד. bedieved? So maybe בדיעבד bedieved. popping
in and out would be okay, but לכתחילה lechatchila? you would still
need direct supervision. That's answer number one. המניח קתני בדיעבד, hamaniach katani
bedieved, it's only after post facto. But לכתחילה lechatchila say אביי Abaye
would say you need direct supervision. So the גמרא gemara continues, רבא
Rava isn't giving up. אלא מהכא, Ela me'hacha, here's another משנה mishna
we have from about from about יין, yayin, about wine of non-Jews.
אינו שומר צריך להיות יושב ומשמר. eino shomer tzarich lihyot yoshev umeshamer.
A similar example, you have a non-Jew handling your wine, with your
barrels of wine, you do not have to be sit and watch
the full time and make sure that nothing goes wrong. אלא אף
על פי שהוא יוצא ונכנס מותר. ela af al pi shehu yotze
venichnas mutar. Even if you're just going in and out it's okay.
And there it sounds like מותר, mutar, לכתחילה. lechatchila לכתחילה lechatchila. it
is sufficient to just pop in and out. So רבא Rava says
ah, for me it suffices to just pop in and out לכתחילה
lechatchila and not to be there constantly. So I disagree with you
in the basic demands of what constitutes necessary supervision. אלא אמר רבא,
ela amar Rava, so רבא Rava is going to say almost the
exact same thing as אביי, Abaye, but change the question about what
is the minimum required. אלא אמר רבא, ela amar Rava, so rather
says רבא, Rava, הכי קתני, hachi katani, here's how to read the
משנה. Mishna. הכל שוחטין, hakol shochtin, all can shecht, ואפילו כותי, va'afilu
kuti, even the
Samaritan. What if he's going to try to mess it up? במה
דברים אמורים, bame devarim amurim, when is this true? כשישראל יוצא ונכנס,
kesheyisrael yotze venichnas, when the יהודי Yehudi is popping in and out.
אבל בא ומצא ששחט, aval ba umatza sheshachat, if you came and
found that he had already shechted, then what do you do with
it after the fact? There was no supervision. חותך כזית בשר ונותן
לו, chotech kezayit basar venoten lo, so you cut off a כזית
kezayit of meat and feed it to him. אכלו, achlo, if he
eats it, מותר לאכול משחיטתו, mutar le'echol mishchitasso, then you can eat
from it because you know he wouldn't eat from it if it
was not כשר. kosher. לא אכלו, lo achlo, if he refuses to
eat from it, אסור לאכול משחיטתו, assur le'echol mishchitasso, you cannot eat
from it because then you suspect that he messed it up, even
unintentionally. חוץ, chutz, with the exception of חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shote
vekatan, that a חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shote vekatan who shechted, דאפילו
דיעבד נמי לא, de'afilu diavad nami lo, even after the fact there's
no way to salvage it, because you can't feed them the meat
because they don't know, they think they did a good job. Why?
שמא ישהו שמא ידרסו שמא יחלידו, shema yishu shema yidresu shema yachlidu,
lest they make any of these errors of pausing or pressure and
so
on. וכולן ששחטו, vekulan sheshachtu, and if any of these shechted with
direct supervision, it's okay. So again we're back to this question, what
does וכולן vekulan mean? אילימא חרש שוטה וקטן, eileima cheresh shote vekatan,
if you're saying that it means if the חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh
shote vekatan shechted with direct supervision it's okay, עלה קאי, ala kai,
you're talking about them. So why did you have to say וכולן,
vekulan, everybody? Just say ואם שחטו ve'im shachtu מבעי, mibaye, if they
shechted with direct supervision. אלא כותי, ela kuti, so רבא Rava would
say it's talking about the
Samaritan. הא אמרת אפילו יוצא ונכנס, ha amart afilu yotze venichnas, you
רבא Rava don't even need direct supervision with the Samaritan, you allow
the guy to be popping in and out. קשיא, kashya, okay, it's
difficult. So both אביי Abaye and רבא Rava have a hard time
explaining that last phrase וכולן vekulan because they would basically say it's
only referring to the חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shote vekatan and then
it could have said a different phrase ואם שחטו, ve'im shachtu, but
okay, they're not bothered with it. So what do we have in
the משנה Mishna so far? We have one explanation which was not
too interesting for us about if you're a טמא tamay person and
you're doing it with טהרת הקודש, taharas hakodesh, whatever, not very relevant.
Although through that we learned, we learned that the שחיטה shechita knife
does not really have to have any status or any formal requirement,
it just has to be sharp and smooth. Okay, that was number
one. Number two is we're talking about what type of people can
shecht and we introduced the whole category of Samaritan, they're Jews, they're
careful about שחיטה shechita but they're not careful about feeding other people
טרפה treifa meat. And through that we discussed what degree of supervision
is necessary. Where אביי Abaye demands generally a משגיח תמידי עומד על
גביו mashgiach tamidi omed al gabav and רבא Rava says יוצא ונכנס
yotze venichnas is enough. Now again I want to point out the
difference between this and the חרש שוטה וקטן. cheresh shote vekatan. חרש
שוטה וקטן cheresh shote vekatan are people that actually don't know what
to do or are physically unable to do it correctly. There nobody
questions like the end of the משנה Mishna says that you need
עומד על גביו, omed al gabav, right? It says if the חרש
שוטה וקטן cheresh shote vekatan shecht ואחרים רואים אותם ve'acherim ro'im osam
are constantly watching. Why? Because the idea of being יוצא ונכנס yotze
venichnas is keeping people honest. Sometimes it's not enough to be honest,
sometimes you have to be competent as well as being honest, right?
I mean, you know, for in general if somebody is dealing with
a כשרות kashrus concern or restaurant or whatever, there are two things
you have to know. Number one is that the people really understand
what the rules are, it's very clear what all the rules and
the requirements are, and number two is they understand the importance about
it and they're honest or they'll be kept honest because you're going
to be checking in on them. Okay, but you need both. It's
so יוצא ונכנס yotze venichnas can keep people honest, but it doesn't
help if they're really not competent and able to do it, which
is why by the חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shote vekatan you need
to directly observe to make sure it was technically done correctly. Whereas
by the כותי, kuti, he knows how to do it, he's competent
in doing it, the question is is he going to be honest
in doing it when it's for somebody else? So that's where there's
the debate of do you need a משגיח תמידי mashgiach tamidi for
that or just a יוצא ונכנס, yotze venichnas, that's the debate of
אביי Abaye and רבא. Rava. Yes, Charlie.
So I can think of a practical application, can we trust it
when our eight-year-old kid has cooked for us?
Right. So yeah, I mean those are similar questions right about, I
mean in general you assume, you mean like if if they really
have no idea about not putting the meat, you know, the meat
with the milk or something like that? Yeah, but then there's also
questions about reporting and can you also trust the reporting in one
of those types of situations? Yeah, so okay, yeah, that is definitely
an interesting one. Now I'm not going to get into the משגיח
תמידי mashgiach tamidi in restaurants because that's not directly,
those types of things anyway are not direct applications of גמרא Gemara
issues, they're more sort of based more on sort of like contextual
types of concerns. But what I will say is the following, a
point that the גמרא Gemara is going to make later on, but
I'm going to introduce it here, which is רבא Rava had pretty
good evidence by the wine that יוצא ונכנס yotze venichnas was enough.
What's, how can אביי Abaye say that you need משגיח תמידי? mashgiach
tamidi? So the גמרא's Gemara going to say the answer later but
I'm just going to introduce it here, which is that it's also
a question about opportunity for somebody to do something wrong and how
much popping in and out is going to affect it. In the
case of the wine, right, if I'm a non-Jew in the store,
I don't have a right to be... touching your wine. I mean,
before we get even הלכה halacha כשרות kashrus concerned, it's your wine,
it's not my wine. What would what would I be doing in
your store opening up the barrel and taking some of the wine?
So there, and if you ever caught me doing anything with the
wine, opening up the barrel, whatever, it's what the heck are you
doing with my barrel, right?
And he would say I'm sampling to see if I want to
buy.
Well, but we're not assuming that that's an accepted norm normative sort
of context. So therefore, because it's easy to catch me red-handed and
I have no excuse to be handling it, so there it's more
obvious that יוצא ונכנס yotzei venichnas works. Popping in and out, all
I have to do is see you with your hand in the
cookie jar and I've caught you, whatever, that's going to keep you
more honest. By the שחיטה shechita case, you gave me the animal
to שחט. shecht. So it's much harder to catch me doing something
wrong and all you have to do is be out for a
second, and in that one second I can do, I can make
a mistake, I can do something wrong. So that is why אביי
Abaye says יוצא ונכנס yotzei venichnas in this case is not enough.
Because in this case you have a right to be handling it,
what you can do wrong you can do wrong in a second.
In that case you need משגיח תמידי. mashgiach tamidi. And that somewhat
goes to Michael's question about like how do we apply these standards
to today's השגחה. hashgacha. And a lot of them have to do
with these sort of contextual circumstances and other types of factors about,
you know, there's not always a formal rule of absolute this, absolute
that. But anyway, here it's debated by אביי Abaye and רבא Rava
in this case.
Just, just to jump on the shoulders of that comment. Yes. The
business that the שומר shomer in a wine storage facility is in
is different than the business of a שוחט. shochet. You're hiring the
wine storage steward to guard your wine, you're hiring the שוחט shochet
to process the food.
So he actually is handling it and changing it.
And so it doesn't even matter what the standards for remuneration are,
because if the שוחט shochet is honest and says I screwed up
your chicken or I screwed up your cow even worse, right, then
even if you're paying him by the hour, so you're not reducing
his wages that given day, if it becomes known that this guy's
not a reliable שוחט, shochet, he's going to lose his business. Right.
So the economic the economic incentives to lie
are on the shoulders of the שוחט. shochet.
So, okay, I'm
trying
to I'm trying to get this, meaning in one case the non-Jew
happens to be hanging around in your store and you're saying
I'm not assuming the case of somebody who's loitering. I'm assuming the
case that, oh, Michael is, Michael is,
oh, no, but that wasn't the case in the משנה. mishna. The
case in the משנה mishna was the non-Jew was loitering and somebody
else was watching to make sure he didn't touch.
How do you know that he's loitering? How do you know that
he's not a worker or something?
Yeah, he could be a worker. Okay, that's true, he could be
a worker.
So he's a worker in the facility, his job is not to
do any of that stuff, he's no economic incentive to do any
of that stuff, that's just to be malicious. Right?
Right. Okay, I see your point. Okay, so you're saying, right. So
you're saying in addition to the point about that the circumstances allow
for it more and it's harder to catch him doing something wrong,
you're also saying that in the שוחט shochet case, he has a
serious economic incentive to lie where the other case it really, right,
the incentive to do something wrong is much less. Okay, that's another
excellent point. Good. So all of those could allow for the fact
that יוצא ונכנס yotzei venichnas works by the wine, but would not
work for the שחיטה shechita and that's the debate of אביי Abaye
and רבא. Rava. Okay, now we go on to a third answer.
Okay, רב אשי אמר הכי קתני. Rav Ashi amar hachi katani. Here's
how to read the משנה. mishna. הכל שוחטין ואפילו ישראל מומר. Hakol
shochtin va-afilu Yisrael mumar. Now that we're talking about people that can
שחט, shecht, which is a reasonable thing to talk about because the
משנה mishna says הכל שוחטין. Hakol shochtin. It's talking about what type
of people. So the first person that we've explored other than the
טמא, tamei, which wasn't so interesting, is the כותי. Kuti. Now we're
going to get to the next person which is very interesting. You
can't explore the non-Jew because the non-Jew is like categorically excluded. There's
no way to say בדיעבד bedieved it's okay, or whatever. But the
next category is the מומר, mumar, the heretic. Now normally we translate
מומר mumar as heretic, but in the גמרא, gemara, מומר mumar really
means somebody who is a violator, a sort of, you know, somebody
who regularly violates law. Okay, and there could be two types of
מומר. mumar. There's a מומר לתיאבון, mumar lete'avon, somebody that regularly violates
out of desire and appetite. I just can't help myself, I'm addicted
to smoking, I smoke on שבת. Shabbos. Or I just love, you
know, pork, and I eat pork, and everything else I'm very, I'm
very careful, I'm super הלכתי, halachic, but this is the one thing
that I do just because I have an overwhelming desire. Okay, that's
one type of a מומר, mumar, מומר לתיאבון. mumar lete'avon. There's another
type of a מומר mumar is a מומר להכעיס, mumar lehach'is, somebody
who has no desire, no really lust or desire for the thing,
but does it to spite God. Okay, I'm doing this just to
show how angry I am with God that I am going to,
you know, eat this stuff even though I don't like it. Okay,
and it's a way, it's an act of spite. A מומר להכעיס
mumar lehach'is is of course much worse because he's really got an
ideological axe to grind, and you know, that might translate into other
ways as well. Okay, so the question is can either of these
two people do שחיטה? shechita? And that's the question we're
going to look at next. How would you handle, what about the
third category of someone who really doesn't care?
Right, so that is a great question which is discussed in contemporary
times, how to apply that.
And it's not discussed in the גמרא gemara because it didn't really
exist so much in the גמרא. gemara. Meaning in the גמרא gemara
you didn't have, you know, we in our times, sometimes I think
of מומר להכעיס mumar lehachis as we would loosely translate it as
somebody who does it because he doesn't believe. But it's not true.
The גמרא Gemara didn't even have a case of somebody who didn't
believe. The גמרא Gemara had a case of somebody, it assumes that
everybody buys into the system, so the worst you can be is
you're doing it in spite, but you're not doing it out of
lack of fundamental belief. And we have people that either don't believe
or are just oblivious, ignorant, you know, either so and that's a
question of how to fit it in. I would say that there
are two issues about the difference and we're about to see it,
so let me give you a short answer to that. There are
two fundamental differences between the מומר להכעיס mumar lehachis and the מומר
לתיאבון. mumar leteavon. One is to what degree does it sort of
invalidate you as a person? You know, and the מומר לתיאבון, mumar
leteavon, okay, you're doing a sin regularly, but it's not like you
have really sort of, you're not like a real רשע, rasha, just
not to the same degree as the מומר להכעיס. mumar lehachis. So
a מומר להכעיס mumar lehachis can sometimes be categorically excluded, not just
because we're afraid about how you'll act, but somebody that sort of
does sins in spite is more categorically a רשע rasha and excluded,
okay? That's one difference. The other difference is even when it's not
talking about labeling the person, how might this translate into other circumstances?
So what we're about to see is that a מומר לתיאבון mumar
leteavon if I'm only doing it out of desire, the assumption is
is that if you put in front of me two equally good
pieces of meat, a steak of נבילה, neveilah, of not-שחטed, shacht and
a steak of something that was שחטed shacht properly. They taste the
exact same. So since I'm only doing it because of my lust
and desire, there's no reason I would choose non-kosher over kosher if
they're the exact same. So everything being equal, I'll choose the kosher.
That's the מומר לתיאבון. mumar leteavon. A מומר להכעיס, mumar lehachis, he's
doing it because he's got a point to make and he's going
to go ahead and he's going to eat the טריפה treif even
if it's just as easy. So in that situation, how will you
act in a given circumstance? There sometimes the person that's completely ignorant
might be more like the מומר להכעיס, mumar lehachis, because if you're
completely ignorant, you're not going to choose the kosher one. You're completely
ignorant of the aspects of כשרות, kashrut, right? So there's nothing would
motivate you to do that and you would just as easily do
the non-kosher. So within הלכה halacha this issue about ignorance and somebody
that does whatever, how to put it into these categories is not
explored in the גמרא Gemara but is definitely explored in later literature.
Okay, so let's take a look now at what we have. הכי
תני, hachi tani,
הכל שוחטין, hakol shochtin, everybody can שחט shecht ואפילו ישראל מומר, vafillu
yisrael mumar, even a ישראל yisrael that is a rebel or a
violator. So מומר mumar to what? What— I wouldn't say a fall—
מומר למאי, mumar lemai, in what ways is he violating?
לאכול נבילות לתיאבון, leechol neveilot leteavon, so we're talking about he will
eat נבילות, neveilot, and נבילות neveilot is very specific, it's not just
a stand-in for like pork and טריפה treif food, pork and lobster,
it specifically means נבילות neveilot because the concern here is if you
don't do a good שחיטה, shechitah, then the meat is a נבילה.
neveilah. So specifically he would go ahead and eat non-שחט shacht meat.
So that's why it's an immediate area of concern because he's prepared
not to be concerned about שחיטה. shechitah. But he does it לתיאבון,
leteavon, out of desire. Now what's the desire? I mean, it tastes
the same as שחט shacht meat, so presumably maybe it's a lot
cheaper would be one thing I would say, okay? So but he's
willing to violate and do נבילות לתיאבון neveilot leteavon out of desire,
out of appetite. וכי הא דרבא, vechi ha derava, like רבא, rava,
דאמר רבא, deamar rava, ישראל מומר אוכל נבילות לתיאבון. yisrael mumar ochel
neveilot leteavon. There's going to be a focus of tomorrow's דף, daf,
now we're just bringing it in incidentally. If you have a Jew
that rebels and that eats נבילות neveilot but out of desire, not
out of an act of spite or rebellion, בודק סכין ונותן לו,
bodek sakin venoten lo, ומותר לאכול משחיטתו. umutar leechol mishechitato. You can
check the knife for him, make sure that it's sharp and smooth
and it's proper, give it to him, and assuming he knows הלכות
שחיטה hilchot shechitah you can eat from his שחיטה. shechitah. Why? Here
the guy that eats non-kosher meat, non-שחט shacht meat, why can you
eat from his שחיטה? shechitah? Because again, we're assuming that he only
does that when there's some benefit for him, some gain, it tastes
better, it's cheaper, there's some gain. Here if you check, not שחט—
shacht check the knife, so you actually have given him, he doesn't
have to do any effort, I'm giving you this knife, it's checked,
you don't even have to check it and smooth it and sharpen
it, a lot of what a שוחט shochet has to do is
worry about the knife. Don't worry, I took care of that for
you. All you gotta do is just do the act. So now
the difference between doing the act correctly and doing the act incorrectly
is so trivial that since there's really no gain in making it
a נבילה, neveilah, so you'll do it, you'll do it correctly. Now
that's the assumption, I gotta tell you that I don't really fully
understand that because you would still think that to do it correctly
requires more attention and more focus than doing it incorrectly. But if
you assume somebody really knows what they're doing and they're an expert
and they've done it before, then it's probably easier to do it
correctly because that's what they're used to doing is just doing it
correctly, right? So the גמרא Gemara assumes that the care that it
takes to do it correctly is not a factor. So as long
as I've checked the knife and it doesn't require any effort on
your part, all you've got to do is just do it correctly,
that you'll
do, אינהו לא משנו, inhu lo mashnu, that you'll do because there's
no benefit to you to do it incorrectly. Okay, now I do
want to point out something interesting which you would never have nowadays
because nowadays with certain types of religious politics, here we're taking a
guy that is a known violator— violator, a known person that regularly
eats נבלה, Neveila, and we're saying okay, but in this circumstance we
can assume that he's going to do it correctly and we don't
even need to supervise him. Okay, like, you know, that would be
scandalous for something like that to take place nowadays, but the גמרא
Gemara is willing to say that. Yes.
Fifty years ago Rav Cutler gave a הכשר Hechsher to a bakery
that was owned by a non-שומר שבת Shomer Shabbos Jew.
Aha. Okay, so there you go.
That wasn't fifty years ago.
Right. Right. All right. So I mean but I think that this
is even one step further than that because he's actually doing the
שחיטה. Shechita. Okay, can you imagine that, having your שוחט Shochet being
a guy that regularly eats non-shechted food? Okay. Anyway, so all right,
so that's what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay. אבל לא בדק ונתן
לו, Aval lo badak v'natan lo, but if you did not check
ahead of time the knife, so you made that his responsibility, which
is a pain in the neck to have to check a knife,
then לא ישחוט, Lo yishchot, you're not allowed to let him shecht.
ואם שחט, V'im shachat, if he did shecht, then בודק סכינו אחריו,
Bodek sakino acharav, then there's still a way to salvage: check the
knife after the fact. Because the knife can only get worse in
the process; it's not going to get better in the process of
shechting. It can only get duller and nicked. It's not going to
get sharper and smooth. So if you check the knife afterwards and
you see that it was good and then the only question now
is, again, did he technically do it correctly? That you can assume
he did. נמצא סכין יפה, Nimtza sakin yafeh, if his knife now
looks good, מותר לאכול משחיטתו, Mutar l'echol meshchitato, you can eat from
his שחיטה. Shechita. ואם לאו, V'im lav, if the knife is not
good
afterwards, אסור לאכול משחיטתו, Assur l'echol meshchitato, you cannot, or if you
didn't shecht, אסור לאכול משחיטתו. Assur l'echol meshchitato. So that's the case
of the מומר. Mumar. That's where you're allowed לכתחילה בדיעבד. L'chatchila b'diavad,
חול, Chol, but it's not the case of חרש שוטה וקטן, Cheresh
shoteh v'Katan, דאפילו בדיעבד נמי לא, D'afillu b'diavad nami lo, even after
the fact you can't use from a חרש שוטה וקטן Cheresh shoteh
v'Katan even if the knife was smooth, because from a חרש שוטה
וקטן Cheresh shoteh v'Katan it's not just about the knife; it's about
knowing that they technically didn't know how to do it correctly. שמא
ישהה שמא ידרס ושמא יחליד. Shema yish'heh shema yidros v'shema yachlid. וכולן
ששחטו, V'chulan sheshachatu, what's that last phrase of וכולן ששחטו V'chulan sheshachatu
going on? אילימא חרש שוטה וקטן, Ilima cheresh shoteh v'Katan, if it's
talking about חרש שוטה וקטן, Cheresh shoteh v'Katan, הלא קאמר, Halo ka'amar,
he just got through talking about that. ואם שחטו מיבעי ליה, V'im
shachatu mibaei lei, it should have said if they shechted. אלא ישראל
מומר, Ella Yisrael mumar, so we're talking about a ישראל Yisrael that
is a מומר Mumar that eats non-shechted food. So why do you
need direct supervision? אי דבדק סכינא ויהיב ליה, I d'badak sakina v'yahiv
lei, if you checked the knife, הא אמרת, Ha amart, שוחט לכתחילה,
Shochet l'chatchila, he's allowed to do it even לכתחילה. lechatchila אלא, Ella,
so here's the case. דלא בדק, D'lo badak, so you didn't check
the knife. So what? Who still needs direct supervision? אי דאיכא לסכינא,
I d'ika l'sakina, if the knife is around, לבדקיה, Livdikei, לבדקיה השתא,
Livdikei hashta, so check the knife. You said you could check the
knife after the fact. ואי דליתא לסכינא, V'i d'leita l'sakina, and now
here's the really important question. And if you don't have the knife
to check, כי אחרים רואין אותו מאי הוי? Ki acherim ro'in oto
mai havei? Who cares that he's supervised? Right? If you don't have
the knife, even if he does it technically correctly in terms of
his physical actions of his hands, but if the knife has a
nick, that's going to invalidate it regardless. דילמא בסכין פגומה קא שחיט,
Dilma b'sakin pguma ka shachit, maybe he used a chipped knife. So
the גמרא Gemara says קשיא, Kashya, you're right. It's difficult how to
explain that last phrase. It's really only going on חרש שוטה וקטן.
Cheresh shoteh v'Katan. Okay, but now let's understand, appreciate everything you've now
been introduced to so far about שחיטה. Shechita. Number one is there
are no requirements of the knife, formal requirements; it has to be
sharp and smooth, but it doesn't have to be a certain type
of an object and vessel and so on. A Samaritan, we assume
is Jewish, knows the laws, will do it correctly, but he might
not care that you're going to eat טרייף Treif meat. So you
have to keep him honest. And there we had two different versions
of keeping him honest, either יוצא ונכנס, Yotzei v'nichnas, popping in and
out, or direct supervision. Also forcing him to eat the meat will
make sure that he actually did it correctly. Then we had the
next case of a Jew who's a מומר, Mumar, a Jew who
doesn't eat, who because of benefit to himself, either taste buds or
cost, will eat meat that's not shechted properly. And surprisingly we find
out that you're allowed to make him a שוחט Shochet as long
as it doesn't require any effort on his part, as long as
you check the knife. What we've also found out is that if
the knife has not been checked beforehand, then even with direct supervision,
it's not going to help anything because you still need to know
that the knife was correct. But this is for everybody though. Right,
that would be for everybody. So what this is getting us to
is a discussion we're going to see later on about the importance
of checking the knife, either before, and if you didn't do it
before, at least afterwards. But if the knife wasn't checked, then no
matter how well you technically did it, that's going to remain a
serious question about whether the שחיטה Shechita was good. Okay. So you
can see through the process of trying to explain this משנה Mishna
as לכתחילה L'chatchila. בדיעבד, bedieved we're introducing a lot of major concepts
about שחיטה. Shechita.
Do we really assume that like you know let's say I checked
it beforehand? Yeah.
But then afterwards it has a nick. That's going to be a
major discussion.
Do we assume like the nick's שחיטה? Shechita?
I'm not going to answer that. That's going to be the גמרא
Gemara coming up in like two days. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says like okay.
רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, so that was רב אשי's Rav
Ashi answer. Now we're up to רבינא. Ravina. רבינא אמר, Ravina amar,
רבינא אמר הכי קתני, Ravina amar hachi katani, here's how you read
it. הכל שוחטים הכל מומחין שוחטין. Hakol shochtin hakol mumchin shochtin. Now
רבינא Ravina does not discuss unusual people: טמא, Tamei, כותי, Kuti, מומר.
Mumar. He talks about what are the... General requirements to שחט shechted
*shecht*, and he talks about two types of people. There are going
to be two versions of רבינא Ravina *Ravina*'s statement. One is a
מומחה mumcheh, *mumche*, the other is a מוחזק muchzak *muchzak*. These are
very reasonable things which you would take for granted you need. A
מומחה mumcheh. *mumche* is somebody who's expert in the law. So before
you let somebody שחט shacht *shecht*, you give him a quiz and
make sure that he can tell you back what are all the
laws. What happens if you do this? What happens if you do
that? What happens if you do this? You know, making sure that
somebody knows the laws before he שחט shacht, *shechts*. That's a מומחה
mumcheh, *mumche*. A מוחזק *muchzak* is somebody with experience, somebody that we've
seen שחט shacht *shecht* is שחט shacht. *shecht* already a number of
times in the past. Obviously those are different. Somebody could know the
practice of doing it without really knowing abstractly what the laws are.
Somebody could totally know the laws and be a complete disaster as
soon as you give him a knife. Right? He A doesn't know
how to handle the knife, and B the גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* is
also going to be concerned that maybe as soon as he sees
blood, he's going to faint and therefore and he's going to ruin
the שחיטה shechitah *shechitah* in the process of doing it. So those
are two separate issues: the knowledge of the laws, the מומחה *mumche*,
and the experience, the מוחזק *muchzak*. Theoretical versus practical. Very good. So
let's take a look. So here's what רבינא Ravina. *Ravina* says. רבינא
Ravina, אמר הכי קתני *Ravina amar hachi katani*, here's what it says.
הכי קתני *hachi katani*, הכל שוחטין hakol shochtin, *hacol shochtin*, everybody can
שחט *shecht* who is it. הכל מומחין שוחטין *hacol mumchin shochtin*, as
long as you're an expert in the law you can שחט *shecht*.
מומחין *mumchin*, and it's enough to be an expert. ואף על פי
שאין מוחזקין *ve'af al pi she'ein muchzakin*, even if you are not
yet experienced, which is pretty surprising. במה דברים אמורים bameh devarim amurim,
*bimmeh devarim amurim*, when is that true? שיודעים בו שיודע לומר הלכות
שחיטה shechitah? *sheyodim bo sheyode'a lomar hilchot shechitah*, when he knows can
tell over the הלכות שחיטה shechitah *hilchot shechitah*, meaning he's a מומחה
*mumche* because you know he's a מומחה *mumche* because you tested him.
אבל אין יודעים בו שיודע לומר הלכות שחיטה shechitah. *aval ein yodim
bo sheyode'a lomar hilchot shechitah*, if you don't know that he can
tell them over, so you don't know that he's a מומחה *mumche*,
לא ישחוט lo yishchot. *lo yishchot*, you cannot שחט *shecht*. שחט *Shecht*.
Because he might not know the laws. ואם שחט ve'im shachat *ve'im
shachat*, if he did שחט *shecht*, then בודקין אותו *bodkin oto*, you
can quiz him after the fact. אם יודע לומר הלכות שחיטה shechitah
*im yode'a lomar hilchot shechitah*, if now he passes the test after
the fact, so presumably he didn't learn it all in the last
ten minutes, so מותר לאכול משחיטתו *mutar leechol mishchitato*, now you can
eat from his שחיטה shechitah *shechitah*. ואם לאו *ve'im lav*, if he
fails the test or you weren't able to test him, אסור לאכול
משחיטתו *assur leechol mishchitato*. So if you don't know either before or
after, obviously preferably before, that this person knew the laws, then you
cannot eat from his שחיטה shechita *shechitah*. Okay, אסור לאכול משחיטתו *assur
leechol mishchitato*, חוץ מחרש שוטה וקטן *chutz meicheresh shoteh vekatan*, except excluding
חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh, shoteh, ve'katan, *cheresh shoteh vekatan*. ואפילו דיעבד נמי
לא *ve'afillu dievad nami lo*, even after the fact it doesn't matter.
Now this is surprising. It means even in an analogous case it's
not going to be by חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh, shoteh, ve'katan. *cheresh
shoteh vekatan*, which means even if you quiz them and they know
the laws, you still cannot eat from the חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh,
shoteh, ve'katan, *cheresh shoteh vekatan*. Why? שמא ישהה שמא ידרוס ושמא יחליד
*shema yish'eh shema yidros shema yachlid*, for them we are concerned not
just even they might be able to know it in the abstract,
but we're still concerned because of their age or because of their
disabilities that they're not going to be able to technically perform it
correctly. More than we would be concerned about a normal person who
didn't have experience. For them in particular we're concerned that they can
say over the laws but not be able to do it in
practice. So that's an interesting new little twist that they might be
able to pass a test in flying colors but you still can't
eat from their שחיטה *shechitah*. Okay. וכולן ששחטו אהאי
*vechulan sheshachatu ahai*, now what does the last phrase mean? Anybody who
שחט *shecht* with direct observation is okay. אילימא *ileima* חרש שוטה וקטן
cheresh, shoteh, ve'katan. *cheresh shoteh vekatan*, if it's just going on חרש
שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh v'katan? *cheresh shoteh vekatan*, אלקאי *alakaye*? We were
just talking about it. ואם שחטו shachtu מיבעי *ve'im shachatu mibei*, it
should have said if they שחט *shecht*, not וכולן *vechulan*. אלא שאין
מומחין *ella she'ein mumchin*, it's somebody that hasn't been tested as an
expert. בבודקין אותו סגי *bebodkin oto sagi*, so that person it's sufficient
to test them after the fact. דליכא קמן דליבדקיה *delyka kaman delyvdekei*,
ah let's say he left, he's not around to quiz him after
the fact. So here you have an interesting lesson. Somebody שחט *shecht*,
you did not you have no know- you did not test them
before or after that he knew the הלכות *halachot*. Can you eat
from his שחיטה *shechitah*? And here the answer is he's no worse
than the חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh v'katan, *cheresh shoteh vekatan*. As
long as it was directly observed and observed to have been done
correctly, that will suffice even though you never had a chance to
quiz him. Again, he's no worse than the חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh
shoteh v'katan, *cheresh shoteh vekatan*. Okay. By the way, I should say
that an implicit assumption throughout all of this is that you get
all the information you need out of observation. Which is an interesting
ques- well plus the knife. The knife is the other thing we
indicated. The knife has to be smooth. But you know, you might
not say that that's true. I mean if one of the problems
is like putting pressure on. Can somebody really see whether somebody is
putting pressure on? Now maybe because when you do it correctly it's
like a quick shhh. It's like you know whatever. To put pressure
maybe causes more but you would imagine that it requires a very
very skilled eye to see you know to catch everything just through
direct observation but that's an ongoing just assumption that the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*'s working with. Okay so what do we have now? We have
חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh v'katan *cheresh shoteh vekatan* it doesn't matter
they know the הלכות *halachot* they always need direct observation. A normal
person needs to know the הלכה halakhah *halachah*. If you don't know
whether they knew the הלכה *halachah* or not, then direct observation will
suffice. It won't be any worse than a חרש שוטה וקטן *cheresh
shoteh vekatan*. Okay, that's one answer of רבינא Ravina? *Ravina*. אלא *ella*
one minute. דליכא קמן *delyka kaman*. Okay yeah go ahead what's your
quest-?
So all the other answers when we say חרש שוטה וקטן *cheresh
shoteh vekatan*, so it means even if someone עומד על גביו omed
al gabav, *omni-al-gabbav-o* it's still not good? Or? The
answers versus?
No, they just... it wasn't necessary. I mean, go back and look
at the specific answers, they basically were saying that you don't even
need עומד על גביו.
So חרש שוטה וקטן, even if עומד על גביו, then they're fine
too?
Yeah, yeah, that's what, right, exactly. Okay, now take a look at
this Tosafot very briefly, דלסקמאן דליבדוקיה. delas keman delivdekieh. Tosafot says, תימה
דמשמע הא איכא קמן ולא ידע. teima de'mashma ha ika kaman velo
yada. The Gemara did not discuss a third possibility. It says tested
him before, tested him after, never got around to testing him. What's
the fourth possibility?
You tested him and he failed. Okay. So if somebody actually doesn't
know, will direct observation be enough? Now you would think after the
fact. You would think the answer should be yes because he wouldn't
be worse than the חרש שוטה וקטן. So if you directly observed,
it should be enough. So Tosafot says why didn't the Gemara say
that? It just said that he's not around. Why didn't it give
an even more extreme case? He failed the test and nevertheless observation
works. So that's his question. תימה דמשמע הא איכא קמן, teima de'mashma
ha ika kaman, if he is around ולא ידע velo yada and
he didn't know the law, תהא שחיטתו כשרה, tehe shechitato kesheira, אף
על גב דחמי להו, af al gav de'chamei lehu, even though other
people see him דשחטי שפיר deshachti shapir that he does good. כמבואר
גבי הא דאמר רב נחמן ראהו ששחט מתחילה ועד סוף מותר לאכול
משחיטתו. kimevo'ar gabei ha de'amar Rav Nachman ra'ahu she'shachat mitechila ve'ad sof
mutar le'echol mishechitato. So the Gemara basically assumes that as long as
you observed, even if he doesn't know the law. So Tosafot doesn't
answer it. But I think we have to assume that if direct
observation works for חרש שוטה וקטן, direct observation will also work for
an adult who doesn't know the law, but was still observed to
do it correctly. And that's basically Tosafot's assumption as well. Okay so
what do we have now? We have the כותי Kuti who it's
basically a question about נאמנות. ne'emanut. We have the מומר mumar who
basically it's a question about removing any incentive for him, any gain
for him to do it incorrectly. Okay, we also have introduced the
idea that no matter how much you observe you gotta check out
the knife. And now we have the final question about what do
we require of a normal person before we allow them to do
that? And the first answer is he has to be a מומחה,
has to know the laws. And if we didn't check before, we
check after. But if they didn't know the laws or we weren't
able to test, but as Tosafot points out, even if he didn't
know the laws, no worse than a חרש שוטה וקטן. And if
it was observed to have been done technically correct, then it will
be good after the fact. Now we get to another version of
רבינא Ravina which is more about experience than it is about knowledge.
So let's take a look.
איכא דאמרי, ika de'amri, others say,
I lost my place. איכא דאמרי רבינא אמר, ika de'amri Ravina amar,
here's what Ravina says. הכי תני, hachi tani, here's how to read
the Mishnah. הכל שוחטין, everybody shechts, הכל מוחזקין שוחטין. hakol muchzakin shochtin.
Anybody with experience is allowed to shecht. Which is a little bit
of circular, how do you get experience if you've never been allowed
to shecht beforehand? But okay, maybe you experience and you don't eat
it, or maybe you experience through direct observation. But when we actually
give you, you know, the ability to shecht and we're going to
leave you alone, that's only if you've actually had experience. מוחזקין אף
על פי שאין מומחין. muchzakin af al pi she'ein mumchin. Now this
is interesting. Experience even if you have not been tested in your
knowledge. Okay, now the question is what does that mean? Does it
mean that literally you don't know, or just means we haven't tested
you? Would we allow somebody לכתחילה lechatchila to be a שוחט shochet
that has had experience that, you know, basically honestly admits I have
no idea what the laws are, I just am doing what, you
know, how I've been apprenticed to do it? Would we allow that
or not? So the assumption here I think Rashi says is אף
על פי שאין מומחין, af al pi she'ein mumchin, Rashi says דלא
ידענא בהו דיידעי להלכות שחיטה. delo yadana behu deyadei lehilchot shechita. He
hasn't been tested. So if somebody honestly admits I don't know what
the laws are, there's a reason to assume we would not let
him do it לכתחילה. lechatchila. But okay, what does Ravina say? Ravina's
saying the primary criterion is experience, we don't have to test you
about your knowledge. Our major concern is are you experienced or not?
Okay. מוחזקין אף על פי שאין מומחין. muchzakin af al pi she'ein
mumchin. הכל שוחטין אף על פי שאין
מומחין. hakol shochtin af al pi she'ein mumchin. במה דברים אמורים,
when is that true? ששחטו לפנינו ב' וג' פעמים. she'shachtu lefanenu shtei
ve'shalosh pe'amim.
Meaning the fact that you have experience is something that we have
witnessed. We see that you've shechted two or three times ולא נתעלף
velo nitalef and you didn't faint in the process. אבל לא שחט
לפנינו ב' וג' פעמים aval lo shachat lefanenu shtei ve'shalosh pe'amim and
if you have not done it and we don't know, so you
might claim you have experience but we don't really know that for
a fact, לא ישחוט. So if you're not known to be experienced,
we will not let you shecht, שמא יתעלף shema yitalef because we're
afraid that you will faint. I would say even before saying faint,
we're afraid that you just won't be able to, you know, to
do the hand motion correctly. You won't have the, you know, that
type of a skill. But either way, if we don't know you're
experienced, we won't let you do it. ואם שחט and if you
did shecht ואמר ברי לי שלא נתעלפתי, ve'amar bari li she'lo nitalafti,
I will tell you that I did not faint and I did
a right job, then שחיטתו כשרה, shechitato kesheira, then it is valid
בדיעבד bedi'avad we allow, we take your word that you're a מומחה.
Right, so this
is actually quite interesting, right? Here's somebody walks off the street, we
haven't tested him for his knowledge, we haven't he doesn't have experience,
he shechts it and he tells us afterwards that he did a
proper job. We trust him. Now that's pretty big חידוש chiddush that
after the fact we trust a guy to say, oh yes I
did it correctly. Especially a surprising fact if we don't know that
he knows the
laws. How can... also be able to know that he knows what
the requirements are. But that's not being spelled out. Yes.
Are we assuming that someone is training him or the father or
because then the person who is training him could testify.
Yeah, but that's a possibility, but that's not being presented here. So
we have to deal with what we have. Now another factor to
consider here is not just his trustworthiness, but something the גמרא Gemara
going to say in a minute that רוב המצויים אצל שחיטה מומחין
הן, rov hametzuyim eitzel shechitah mumchin hein,
which basically means most people who have the חצפה chutzpah to pick
up a knife and approach a 2,000-pound steer know what they're doing.
Okay, so we're going to work with the assumption that, you know,
that if you went ahead and did it, you probably, either you
were grossly, you know, irresponsible or you probably did know what you
were doing. So this is interesting. So now it's interesting. We know
לכתחילה lechatchila either he has to be tested for his knowledge or
לכתחילה lechatchila he has to have—we have to know he has experience,
but בדיעבד bediavad it seems like we'll trust the guy to say,
"I did the job correctly," even if there was no, you know,
way of ensuring that he actually knew what—you know, direct evidence that
he knew what he was doing or that he had experience.
So what do you make of the negative outcome that was listed
in this case versus the חרש שוטה וקטן?
You
mean—you mean why there are we always require direct observation?
No, in the case of the חרש שוטה וקטן, we're saying that
they're not going to perform the שחיטה appropriately. They're going to do
specific things that are wrong. Right.
In this case, not just because they don't know, because they're not
able. Right.
Whatever it is, that
seems to be the assumption, right,
that the process
is ineffective. Right. In this case, it's
שנתעלף. shenisaleif. Is it concern about
the—the guy who's doing the שחיטה?
No, no, no. If he fainted, then he's improperly doing the שחיטה
because then he's pausing, he's whatever. No, the assumption is that the
fainting—I'm sorry I didn't make that clear—the assumption is that the fainting
will mess up the שחיטה. Okay. Alright, so, ואם שחט ואמר ברי
לי שלא נתעלפתי, v'im shachat v'amar bari li shelo nisalafti, I know
I didn't faint, שחיטתו כשרה, shechitah k'sheirah, valid. חוץ מחרש שוטה וקטן
דאפילו בדיעבד נמי לא, chutz micheresh shoteh v'katan d'afilu bediavad nami lo,
there בדיעבד bediavad it's not good because there it's not about trusting
or whatever, it's about do they really know what they're doing? שמא
ישהו שמא ידרסו ושמא יחלידו, shema yish'hu shema yidresu v'shema yachlidu, because
maybe they made those mistakes. וכולן ששחטו ואחרים רואין אותן, v'chulan sheshachtu
v'acherim ro'in otan, and anyone who שחטו with direct observation is good.
ועל דא קאי, v'al da kai, where's that going on? אילימא אחרש
שוטה וקטן לא קאי, ilima acheresh shoteh v'katan lo kai, if it's
חרש שוטה וקטן, we just got through with them, ודאי שחטו מיבעי
ליה, v'dai shachtu mibei leh, it should have said ודאי שחטו. v'dai
shachtu. אלא אשאינו מוחזק, ela ashe'eino munchzak, somebody who is not—is not—we
don't know is experienced. ואמרת בברי לי סגי, v'amarta b'bari li sagi,
if he reports it's good enough? So the גמרא Gemara says דליתא
דנשייליה, d'leisa d'nishaylei, it's a case where he's not around to report,
so there direct observation suffices. Okay, so what do we have? We
have by חרש שוטה וקטן you can only go with direct observation.
We have by the כותי Kuti you need the checking in and
out to make sure that you're keeping him honest or observation to
ensure he's honest. You know by the guy that normally eats non-שחט
meat
that there obviously—that you have to remove an incentive for him not
to do a good job, you have to check the knife. And
but even there direct observation won't be good unless the knife is
checked. So we've also learned a principle that the knife has to
be checked. And now we're getting to the core of what is
the normal requirement we have for a normal person before we let
him be a שוחט. shochet. And we have two versions of רבינא.
Ravina One is you have to test him in his knowledge. You
don't have to actually know that he's that experienced before. He's not
afraid people will faint, which is—seems like a very bizarre idea because,
you know, it seems like just knowing things is not enough.
And—but בדיעבד, bediavad, even if he didn't know, again if it was
directly observed and correct, it's done correctly, as long as it was
directly observed, direct observation always helps. And then the other case is
somebody had to have experience.
Whether it's enough—whether he can really not know the laws or just
we don't know if he knows the laws is not clear. רש״י
Rashi says we don't know if he knows the laws. If he
really doesn't know, it's hard to imagine that we would allow him
to do it לכתחילה lechatchila just because he has experience. Presumably, we
might not have to test him, but we presumably we have to
assume that he knows the laws. But again, בדיעבד, bediavad, if he
did it without—without us knowing that he had experience, we will trust
his reporting. And this is I think and—or certainly direct observation will
be okay. So I would say the biggest חידוש chidush that we've
come out here, in addition to the לכתחילה lechatchila question of knowledge
versus experience, is somebody that just reports that he did the job
correctly, do we trust that person? And again the question is how
can you fully trust it unless you know that he knows what
it means to do the job correctly? So that is sort of
not fully explored at this point. Now we're just going to sort
of wrap this up. Yes, Bob.
I'm wondering, you can't have experience until you start doing something.
Well, that's what I said. So you could have experience, but you
could do it under
direct... So now the גמרא's Gemara just going to wrap up why
everybody didn't say what everybody else said. So let's take a look.
Okay. רבינא ורבה בר עולא כי אביי ורבא ורב אשי לא אמרי.
Ravina ve-Rabbah bar Ulla ke-Abaye ve-Rava ve-Rav Ashi lo amri. So רבינא,
Ravina which was the last one, and רבה בר עולא, Rabbah bar
Ulla, who I forget at this stage what he said, anyway, they
didn't say like the three of אביי, Abaye, רבא, Rava, and רב
אשי Rav Ashi משום דקשיא להו בכולן. mishum de-kashya lehu be-khullan. Because
if you remember, some of the answers before were not able to
sufficiently explain the phrase of בכולן be-khullan at the end of the
משנה. Mishnah. So that's why they didn't like those answers. כולהו כרבה
בר עולא לא אמרי. Kullehu ke-Rabbah bar Ulla lo amri. They didn't
say like, oh right, רבה בר עולא Rabbah bar Ulla was the
first answer about טומאה, tumah, which was the least interesting of them.
So why didn't people like the טומאה tumah answer? להך לישנא דאמרת
הכא עיקר, Le-hach lishna de-amart hacha ikkar, because we already know the
principle that a טמא tamei person לכתחילה le-chatchilah shouldn't שחט קדשים kodashim
but בדיעבד be-di'avad it's okay. So we had two explanations. One was
that here is the fundamental place and it was put in, it
was also mentioned in זבחים Zevachim as a, you know, it was
thrown in. אדרבה התם עיקר דבקדשים קאי. Addaraba hatam ikkar de-ve-kodashim ka'ei.
No, it shouldn't have been said here at all, it was enough
to have said it over there in זבחים Zevachim the idea of
a טמא tamei person שוחט. shochet. ולהך לישנא דאמרת התם עיקר, U-le-hach
lishna de-amart hatam ikkar, and even according to the version that said
that over there, the טמא tamei person שוחט shochet really is fundamentally
in זבחים Zevachim and here it was just thrown in as an
aside, והכא איידי דתנא טמא בחולין תנא נמי טמא במוקדשים, ve-hacha aidi
de-tana tamei be-chullin tana nami tamei be-mukkadashim, since here we're talking about
a טמא tamei person שוחט shochet non-sanctified animal, we're also going to
talk about a טמא tamei person שוחט shochet sacrifices. טמא בחולין גופא
לא איצטריכא ליה. Tamei be-chullin gufah lo itztaricha leh. No, there was
no need for the משנה Mishnah to talk about a טמא tamei
person שוחט shochet חולין. chullin. Why not? חולין שנעשו על טהרת קדש,
Chullin she-na'asu al toharat kodesh, even if you're treating non-sanctified food like
קדש, kodesh, like sanctified food, לאו כקדש דמי. lav ke-kodesh dami. It
does not have that halakhic status and there is no need to
avoid, you know, as a טמא tamei person to talk about whether
you're allowed to or not allowed to touch it because it doesn't
really give the food any status. So they didn't say the טומאה
tumah answer. I would say they didn't say the טומאה tumah answer
because it's completely unrelated to the issues of חולין chullin and uninteresting,
but the גמרא Gemara is sort of saying it in a different
variation that they didn't say it because they didn't feel that there
is ever a case of חולין chullin that we have to care
about טומאה. tumah. Even if you're treating it like הקדש, hekdesh, we
never really have to care about it. That's why they didn't like
that answer. Now, כולהו כרבינא לא אמרי. Kullehu ke-Ravina lo amri. Now
how about רבינא? Ravina רבינא has the nicest answers. His was about
מוחזק or מומחה, which was really getting to the heart of what
do we require from a שוחט. shochet. So why didn't they say
רבינא's answer? להך לישנא דאמר מומחין אין שאין מומחין לא, Le-hach lishna
de-amar mumchin in she-ein mumchin lo,
according to the version that you first have to know the guy's
an expert and only then do you let him שחט, רוב מצויין
אצל שחיטה מומחין הן. rov metzuyin etzel shechitah mumchin hen. That's what
I told you before. It's true the guy does have to know
the laws, but there's no requirement for us to give him a
test. We're going to, we can work with an assumption that anybody
that presents himself to do the שחיטה you know knows the laws.
Nobody would do it, or almost nobody would ever present themselves to
do שחיטה if they didn't know the laws. So we agree knowledge
is required, but we don't agree that it's required to test the
person. We're going to assume that the knowledge is had. Okay? So
that's why they would not have read it that way. להך לישנא
דאמר מוחזקין אין שאין מוחזקין לא, Le-hach lishna de-amar muchzakin in she-ein
muchzakin lo,
according to the version that he says you have to have experience
and without experience, no, that's also not true. לאלופי לא חיישינן, Le-allufei
lo chashinan, we're not concerned about fainting. To me, that is the
biggest surprise. Meaning, I can come and I admit I've learned all
the laws, test me, whatever, I have never שחט an animal before
in my life. No problem. Take this knife, take this cow, go
ahead, have a ball. Okay? So that I don't understand. I understand
saying that most people don't faint, maybe, but even if I'm not
actually fainting, that I would be upset and that would make me
slip, or I just don't have the practice, the experience of how
to use the, how to use the knife. So that I really
don't understand, but that's what the גמרא's Gemara saying. So by the
way, this becomes now a very important הלכה discussion. We all agree
that I have to know the law. We all agree that I
have to physically be able to do it. The question is, what
degree do you have to, you know, what assumptions can you make
and what degree do you have to test me? So רבינא said,
well, we can't assume knowledge, we have to test it. Or another
version is, we can't assume the ability to actually do it correctly,
you have to have experience. Now the גמרא Gemara is rejecting both
of those and prepared to say we will assume knowledge as soon
as you present yourself and we will assume that if you know
the laws, you'll be able to actually, actually do it in practice.
Okay, the second one certainly to me is an enormous חידוש. chiddush.
So the question also is going to be how do we rule,
but now we have a very interesting range of issues in terms
of what are the criteria, you know, in theory and what do
you have to be tested on before we actually allow you to
שחט. Yes.
Past qualification today, I say that I'm knowledgeable of the כשרות, kashrut,
there's no reason why you shouldn't eat the food from my kitchen.
Right. Am I supposed to accept that?
Right, that's exactly the same type of a thing. Okay, so let's
just finish this up, we're already a little bit over. So the
גמרא says like this: רבא, Rava, okay, רבא לא אמר כאביי. Rava
lo amar ke-Abaye. רבא Rava didn't say like אביי Abaye about the
משגיח תמידי, mashgiach temidi, כי קשיא, ki kashya, because he didn't believe
you needed a משגיח תמידי. mashgiach temidi. He thought that יוצא ונכנס,
yotzei ve-nichnas, a periodic checkup was okay. אביי לא אמר כרבא. Abaye
lo amar ke-Rava. אביי Abaye didn't say like רבא Rava where the
periodic checkup... even though רבא Rava had evidence from יין נסך yayin
nesech that periodic checking up is enough, יוצא ונכנס, yotzei venichnas, popping
in and out, for the reason I told you earlier. התם לא
נגע, הכא נגע. hasam lo naga, hacha naga. Over there he hasn't
yet touched the wine. So popping in and out will keep him
honest. He doesn't want to get his hand in the cookie jar.
But here where he actually is handling the meat, it's a lot
harder to keep the person honest and you need direct observation. רב
אשי לא אמר כשמעתיה, Rav Ashi lo amar kishmayse, רב אשי Rav
Ashi rejected both of those explanations about the כותי Kuti and popping
in and out, קסבר כותי גרי אריות הן kasavar Kuti Gerei Arayos
hen because he holds that כותים Kutim are not true converts, but
converts because of the lions, because they were scared, that's the whole
story over there in ירמיהו. Yirmiyahu. So he doesn't hold that they're
Jewish. So we can't be discussing כותים Kutim because obviously it's not
good, they weren't Jewish. That's why he didn't do their version. אביי
לא אמר כרב אשי, Abaye lo amar ke'Rav Ashi, why didn't אביי
Abaye take רב אשי's Rav Ashi approach about the מומר, mumar, the
Jew that will eat non-kosher meat? Because לא סבירא ליה הדרבא, lo
svira lei haderava, he doesn't hold like רבא, Rava, he doesn't agree
that giving a מומר mumar a sharpened knife is enough. He thinks
if this guy eats non-kosher meat, I'm not going to trust him
to do my שחיטה even if there's not an incentive for him
to do it
incorrectly. אלא רבא, מאי טעמא לא אמר כשמעתיה? Ela Rava, mai taama
lo amar kishmayse? Why did not רבא Rava say like his own
teaching? רבא Rava was the one that said that you can give
a מומר mumar a sharpened knife. So why didn't he give that
explanation of the משנה mishnah which was a case of the מומר
mumar like רב אשי Rav Ashi did? The גמרא says לדיברי דאביי
קאמר וליה לא סבירא ליה. lidvarei de'Abaye ka'amar velei lo svira lei.
He was just responding to אביי. Abaye. He said, you אביי, Abaye,
that you want to talk about a כותי, Kuti, don't demand that
there be a regular משגיח mashgiach there, it's enough for a guy
popping in and out. So he was like critiquing אביי. Abaye. But
you're right, personally he would have explained the משנה mishnah like רב
אשי Rav Ashi about the Jew that doesn't eat kosher meat, that
it's enough to give him a pre-sharpened knife. Okay, so in this
context we've had a wonderful opportunity to look at a range of
people: the כותי, Kuti, you know, popping in and out, משגיח תמידי,
mashgiach tamidi, the מומר, mumar, whether you remove an incentive for him
to do it wrong, are you able to trust him? And then
particularly רבינא's issues, which I think are the most interesting, are knowledge
and experience and to what degree you have to test for that.
So all of this is going to continue to come up.